Our amazing soccer game is coming on, and there's just one last element that we want to add, and we
want to make the field a little bit more interesting.
At the moment, we've just got a sort of really basic field.
We want to show you how you can just color it in and draw some lines on it, etc. and so that's what
we're going to cover in this lesson.
And then we're going to combine that into our main soccer program.
And you're going to be ready for all the action.
If you look at this code over here for the field, you'll see there's quite a lot.
And it looks a bit weird and confusing.
So this is really where you have to start playing around.
And this did take a lot of trial and errors to get it exact.
But let's get into it and see what it is doing.
Our first line again is importing turtles so we can use all the turtle functions.
Just as an aside, you know we're using these functions like drawing and changing colors and all those
sort of things.
As we said earlier, you don't have to know all of these things.
Simply go and look at the documentation So you can say, I want to look at the turtle function, and
it'll show you all of the things that you can do with that turtle function.
It's not difficult.
So you want to know, oh, can I draw?
How do I lift the pen or how do I put a pen down?
Or how do I change what the turtle is?
All of that is in the documentation.
So it's not something you actually have to remember.
You will start to remember it the more you use it.
But all of that is available in the documentation for Python.
So our function here is just called draw field and it's pretty self-explanatory.
We want it to draw the field.
So basically just the lines on the field and make it look more interesting.
We've created this variable here called field which is just a turtle like we had before with the goalie
and the ball.
We have made the shape a circle, which that can be anything.
It's just something that's drawing.
And we've we've hidden the turtle.
Just so you don't actually see the turtle going around, uh, the whole time.
But obviously you don't.
This isn't really necessary.
That's just kind of for fun.
Yeah.
If you like seeing turtles draw, then that's fine.
But just.
We didn't want the turtle to be seen.
We wanted the drawing to look like it happened by magic.
Yeah, but we still.
You will see the field being drawn out because, well, that's just how Turtle Graphics works.
And then we do a whole lot of and a whole lot of other stuff underneath that.
Uh, I'm not going to go through every single line because I've pretty much explained what all these
functions do in the previous lecture.
A lot of them are pretty obvious.
It's obvious what pen size does.
It's obvious what go to does pen down.
So we've covered all of these.
And just by reading it.
That's the nice thing about the code.
You can literally now read it with your experience and what you've been through and understand what
it's doing.
Yeah.
So this is just moving the turtle to different parts on the screen.
It has to be lifted up at certain times because we don't want lines all the way around.
And yeah, this is fiddling around and trying to make it the perfect field.
But yeah, it just takes practice.
But the main thing you just need to know what.
All these different functions do, which you should already know.
The one I do want to point out though is this for loop over here.
Now what this for loop is doing is it's actually telling the our turtle to draw a semicircle.
Now how it's doing that is it's saying for x in range 180.
And the reason it's 180 is because if you think about it, a semicircle would be 180 degrees because
a full circle is 360.
So for each x in 180 we want it to move forward once.
So basically all that's doing is each time this for loop runs it's moving the field, the field turtle
forward once and turning it to the right by an angle of one or by a degree of one.
So very slowly you'll see it is going to draw a semi-circle because each time the loop's going, it's
moving by one.
Turning the turtle by one.
Moving by one.
Turning the turtle by one until it's done 180 times and made a semi-circle.
And if you can't really imagine that, you could turn the turtle.
So you could actually see the turtle in the drawing as we've turned it off, and you'll actually see
the turtle turning as it slowly draws that 180 degree semicircle.
Yeah, and that will slow everything down quite a bit, but it will definitely help you see what's happening.
And we have two semicircles so we have another one here.
And the reason you'll see that one's right.
That one's left.
It's still doing the same thing.
It's just drawing it from a different side.
But yeah and changing this is just going to make your circle bigger or smaller or your semicircle bigger
or smaller.
So yeah.
Change that number.
See what happens.
Um, yeah.
Just play around.
I think, you know, all these other functions, maybe just this one you haven't seen before.
What that does is it just makes a stamp of the turtle wherever it is on our screen.
So literally it just makes a stamp and the turtle carries on doing what it was meant to.
Then right at the bottom of all of this, I am calling our function draw field.
So by calling it here, it is going to be doing all of this over here.
Now we want to add our field to our game.
So just like we have these other modules called Turtle and Random field now becomes its own module.
So every file program we have that and this and the others we've created are all their own modules.
So if I now want the field module to be seen in the module I have to import it.
Now one thing you need to know is when you save your files.
If you haven't saved the soccer module and the field module in the same folder, It's not going to like
it, and it's going to be confused, and it actually won't be able to find where this field module is.
If you don't want them in the same folder, you have to put the whole path in and it gets a bit confusing.
But for now, just know save these two modules in the same file.
And that's all that's changed on this side.
So let's now run it.
Here you see it's creating one of our semi-circles.
So you can kind of tell that it's slowly turning and moving by 1 or 2 each time to create this little
semicircle here.
And we have our ball and we have our turtle.
So if we click off and now it just looks a little bit more exciting and we can keep on doing it like
we did before.
You'll also see now that the reason I made our angle a maximum angles 27 before and did all those sort
of random numbers is because the size of this only allows for the angle to be a maximum of 27.
And that means that this ball will never go out of this goalie box.
It won't end up over here or over here.
Yeah.
So that's our game.
Go ahead, type out the code, copy it, ask us questions if you're confused.
But really, everything that's here you should understand.
They all very self-explanatory functions.
The names all seem to make sense.
And I think you should be fine to.
Now go and finish up your game you have been creating.
You also notice that in the game we've put in lots of comments just to help you as well to try and explain
every line of code.
So again, as Sarah said, it's all in the practice.
It's all in the playing.
So feel free to take the code, edit little things, change it, see what it does because that's how
you're going to learn.
So you've achieved this amazing goal.
You've actually been able to create your own game.
So give it a try.
Do what we've done there, make the game, tweak it and show us what you can do, that you can be an
amazing programmer in Python.